Women's Organization for National Prohibition Reform (WONPR), Connecticut Division Financial Records
The Lewis Walpole Library
Women's Organization for National Prohibition Reform (WONPR), Connecticut Division Financial Records
1930-1934
LWL MSS 24
The Lewis Walpole Library
9.4
12 boxes + 2 broadsides
The Women's Organization for National Prohibition Reform (WONPR), Connecticut Division Financial Records hold correspondence, donation records and acknowledgements, invoices, receipts, account books, bank records, financial reports, and other documents related to the organization's activities in the state of Connecticut. Although the records do not contain corporate minutes or program-related internal memoranda and correspondence, the division's financial records do provide granular documentation of the workings of the Connecticut chapter.
Women's Organization for National Prohibition Reform. Connecticut Division
Hewes, Philip, 1902-1998
Lewis, Annie Burr Auchincloss, 1902-1959
Crusaders, Inc
Schutz Group Photographers (Washington, D.C.)
Tenschert Photo Co. (Washington, D.C.)
Conditions Governing Access
This material is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Bequest of Wilmarth Sheldon Lewis (Yale 1918), 1979.
Arrangement
Organized into four series: I. Correspondence and Administrative Records, 1930-1933. II. Invoices and Receipts, 1930-1933. III. Accounts and Financial Reports, 1930-1934. IV. The Crusaders, Inc., 1930-1932.
Women's Organization for National Prohibition Reform (WONPR)
The Women's Organization for National Prohibition Reform (WONPR), founded in 1929 by Pauline Morton Sabin, had as its goal the repeal of the Eighteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution, which established the prohibition of alcoholic beverages by declaring as illegal the production, transport, and sale of alcohol. Formed partly in response to the political corruption and flourishing organized crime connected to Prohibition, and to the hypocrisy of politicians who publicly supported Prohibition but enjoyed alcohol in private, the non-partisan volunteer association claimed 300,000 members by spring 1931 and more than 1,000,000 when the amendment was repealed in December 1933. The organization was self-supporting through dues, contributions, and fund-raising events. Their repeal message was also spread by the WONPR speakers' bureaus which sent members out to address audiences in women's social clubs, professional and union meetings, public rallies, and other venues.
Annie Burr Auchincloss Lewis (1902-1959)
Annie Burr Auchincloss Lewis was born in Newport, Rhode Island, on July 22, 1902, the daughter of Emma Jennings Auchincloss and Hugh Dudley Auchincloss. She attended Miss Porter's School in Farmington, Connecticut, and married Wilmarth Sheldon Lewis in New York in 1928; the couple settled in Farmington where Annie Lewis became involved in many charitable and philanthropic activities. She died in Hartford, Connecticut, on May 9, 1959.
Scope and Contents
The Women's Organization for National Prohibition Reform (WONPR), Connecticut Division Financial Records hold correspondence, donation records and acknowledgements, invoices, receipts, account books, bank records, financial reports, and other documents related to the organization's activities in the state of Connecticut.
In her capacity as treasurer of the Connecticut Division of WONPR, Annie Burr Lewis was responsible for forwarding to the national office in New York all income collected statewide. In addition, she paid the bills for setting up and running the administrative office at 1109 Chapel Street, New Haven, and for events taking place around the state. The series holds invoices and receipts covering expenses for printing posters, handbills, and window cards, renting chairs and banners for meetings, and cash for paying the "sandwich men" hired to carry pro-repeal signs at rallies and election polls. Another income stream resulted from the sale of WONPR-branded merchandise—such as cigarette boxes and matchbox cases, scarves and ties, stickers, pins, playing cards, and thimbles—which the Connecticut division produced itself or purchased from the national office, and sold to members or at rallies; examples of WONPR smoking accessories are in the Lewises' household objects collection.
Although the collection does not contain corporate minutes or program-related internal memoranda and correspondence, the division's financial records do provide granular documentation of the workings of a state chapter of WONPR under the direction of president Margaret Bush Clement (1899-1993) of New Haven. The records range from receipts from the maintenance of typewriters in the New Haven office, to tabulations of individual members' contributions, to files of attendance forms generated by the series of "chain lunches" the women held in their homes throughout the state to raise interest in, and money for, WONPR. Other financial records include ledgers, reports, and bank statements, as well as a binder holding bookkeeping course lessons, which Annie Lewis likely used to train herself to keep the books. Also present are four folders of correspondence, documents, and ephemera related to the work of the Connecticut division of The Crusaders, Inc., a men's anti-prohibition organization. Hartford resident Philip Hewes (1902-1998), treasurer of the Connecticut Crusaders, gave the material to Wilmarth Lewis in April 1976. With his gift Hewes included a printed silk "Repeal" necktie he had purchased from WONPR in the early 1930s, an example of the merchandise documented in Series II above.
Men -- Societies and clubs; Prohibition -- Societies, etc.; Prohibition -- United States; Women -- Societies and clubs; Women political activists -- United States; Account books; Financial records; Neckties; Panoramas; Women political activists -- United States; Clement, Margaret Livingston Bush, 1899-1993; Hewes, Philip, 1902-1998; Lewis, Annie Burr Auchincloss, 1902-1959; Crusaders, Inc; Schutz Group Photographers (Washington, D.C.); Tenschert Photo Co. (Washington, D.C.); Women's Organization for National Prohibition Reform; United States. Constitution. 18th Amendment; Lewis, W. S. (Wilmarth Sheldon), 1895-1979
- Correspondence and Administrative Records, 1930–1933; Series I; 1.7; 4 boxes + 1 broadside
  Scope and Contents
  Series I holds administrative correspondence and documents related to the organization's finances and programs. Primarily the records of contributions and contributors, the bulk consists of acknowledgement notes sent by Annie Burr Lewis in response to general donations and those brought in by the WONPR chain lunch program.
  - Advertising and public relations, 1930–1932 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Administrative documents, 1932–1933 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Cates, Mary, 1931–1932 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Mary Cates was chair of the Speaker's Bureau.
  - Cleveland and Washington trips, 1930; 1933 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Contribution records
    - Acknowledgement notes
      - General contributors, 1930–1932 (Box 1, Folder 5-11)
      - General contributors, 1933 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - Repeal Ratification campaign contributors, 1933 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Chain lunch forms and acknowledgments
      Biographical / Historical
      The WONPR chain lunches were hosted by women in communities across the state who invited other women into their homes to dine and discuss the anti-prohibition movement. Those guests then signed up to hold lunches in their own homes, to repeat the agenda and spread the organization's message.
      The report forms list the hostess, with names and addresses of attendees, most of whom were friends and neighbors in Connecticut.
      - Reports of lunches held in May and June 1–6, 1932 (Box 2, Folder 3-8)
      - Reports of lunches held June 7 through the fall, 1932 (Box 3, Folder 1-3)
    - Contribution lists, 1930–1933 (Box 3, Folder 4)
      Primarily typed reports organized by county.
    - Contributor cards, undated (Box 4)
      Printed cards with slots into which contributors were to insert dimes, quarters, and fifty-cent pieces for mailing to the organization.
      Arrangement
      The cards are filed alphabetically by county and thereunder by town.
  - WONPR correspondence, 1930–1933 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    Letters received from the national office in New York.
  - WONPR national financial policies and procedures, 1932 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Other correspondence, 1930–1933 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Photographs, 1931–1933 (Box 5 (Broadside))
    Five panoramic photographs of WONPR women in Washington, DC, at the following events: White House visit, April 15, 1931; Third Annual Convention, April 1932 (members assembled on the east front steps of the Capitol, and at the banquet); and Fourth Annual Convention banquet, April 3, 1933 (two copies).
- Invoices and Receipts, 1930–1933; Series II; 0.84; 2 boxes
  The series contains material that documents the expenses incurred by the organization for its programs and administration. Also here are the records of the paid staff in the New Haven office, as well as organizers in other parts of the state.
  Series II is organized into three subseries: Events, Merchandise, and Office Expenses.
  - Events
    - Banners, booths, and displays, 1930–1933 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Chair rentals, 1930–1933 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Hall rentals, 1931–1932 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Hartford mass meeting at Bushnell Memorial Hall, 1932 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Manchester rally, March 20, 1932 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Sandwich men, 1932 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Merchandise
    Examples of WONPR-branded merchandise can be found in the Lewises' household objects collection, in addition to the single "Repeal" necktie present in Series IV.
    - Diamond Match Company, 1932 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Stehle Silks Corporation, 1932–1933 (Box 6, Folder 8)
      Receipts for scarves, ties, and handkerchiefs ordered by the Connecticut Division.
    - WONPR national office items, 1931–1933 (Box 6, Folder 9)
      Invoices for WONPR-branded merchandise sent to Connecticut for sale in the office and at rallies.
    - Miscellaneous vendors, 1932–1933 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Resale pricelist, undated (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Sales and inventories, 1932–1933 (Box 6, Folder 12)
      Includes records for sales during "Repeal Week," May 16-26, 1932.
  - Office Expenses
    - Freight, 1932–1933 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Insurance, 1932–1933 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Postage, 1931–1933 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Postal-Telegraph Cable Company, 1931–1933 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Printing
      Invoices and receipts for engraving and printing for letterhead, ballots, posters, enrollment cards, and other print pieces by companies in New Haven, Hartford, and around the state. Proofs of photoengraved portraits of WONPR members, and other WONPR graphics, are attached to some invoices; a portrait of Annie Lewis is with the Rundbaken Engraving Company invoice of December 29, 1932.
      - Hunter Press, 1930–1932 (Box 6, Folder 17)
      - Quinnipiack Press, Inc., 1930–1932 (Box 6, Folder 18)
      - Rundbaken Engraving Company, 1932–1933 (Box 6, Folder 19)
      - Swan Engraving Company, 1932 (Box 6, Folder 20)
      - Van Dyck & Company, 1932–1933 (Box 6, Folder 21)
      - Other printers, 1930–1933 (Box 6, Folder 22)
    - Southern New England Telephone Company, 1930–1933 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Staff
      - Falconer, Blanche, 1930–1933 (Box 7, Folder 2)
      - Gilligan, Peter, 1931–1933 (Box 7, Folder 3)
      - Gorska, Adela, 1931–1933 (Box 7, Folder 4)
      - Other employees, 1930–1932 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Student Typewriting Bureau, 1930–1933 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Typewriter maintenance, 1930–1933 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - United Illuminating Company, 1930–1933 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Western Union, 1930–1933 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Whitlock's Bookstore, Inc., 1930–1933 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Yale Cooperative Corporation, 1930–1933 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Yale University (rent), 1930–1933 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Miscellaneous expenses, 1930–1933 (Box 7, Folder 13)
- Accounts and Financial Reports, 1930–1934; Series III; 6.42; 5 boxes
  Series III holds financial records for the organization, including bank check registers and statements, accounting volumes, and financial statements.
  - Audited financial statements, 1932–1933 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Banking records
    - First National Bank & Trust Company, Bridgeport, 1932–1933 (Box 8, Folder 2)
      Account kept by Eleanor Wheeler.
    - West Hartford Trust Company
      Account kept by Annie Lewis.
      - Bank book, 1930 (Box 8, Folder 3)
      - Check registers, 1930–1934 (Box 8, Folder 4-5)
      - Bank statements, 1930–1934 (Box 8, Folder 6-7)
  - Cash book, 1930–1931 (Box 9 (Oversize))
  - General journal, 1930–1932 (Box 10 (Oversize))
    Contains accounts of cash received, cash disbursed, and distributions.
  - General journal, 1932–1933 (Box 11 (Oversize))
  - Journal, 1930–1933 (Box 12 (Oversize))
    Chronological record of contributions with names of contributors.
  - Ledger, 1930–1934 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Petty cash book, 1931–1932 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Petty cash reports, 1930–1933 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Receipt books, 1932–1933 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Treasurer's reports, 1931–1933 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Certified bookkeeping course notebook, circa 1930 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Bookkeeping workbook (blank), circa 1930 (Box 13, Folder 7)
- The Crusaders, Inc., 1930–1932; Series IV; 0.42
  The Crusaders, Inc., was a men's anti-prohibition movement founded on January 16, 1930, in Cleveland, Ohio. The treasurer of the Connecticut branch was Philip Hewes, who presented Wilmarth Sheldon Lewis with an envelope of Crusaders' material in April 1976; it was added to the WONPR records in 2018.
  The series holds a small group of correspondence, documents, and ephemera related to the work of the Crusaders in Connecticut, including a receipt for their certificate of incorporation and a program and financial accounting for the Anti-Prohibition Mass Meeting held in Hartford on January 28, 1932, an event co-sponsored by WONPR. Also present is a "Repeal" necktie, of the type documented in the folder for Stehle Silks Corporation (Box 6, folder 8).
  - Correspondence, 1931–1932 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Hartford mass meeting at Bushnell Memorial Hall, 1932 (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - "Repeal" necktie, circa 1932 (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - Newspaper clipping, 1930 July 31 (Box 14 (Broadside))
    A clipping from the Hartford Daily Courant, with an advertisement for The Crusaders, Inc., which outlines the organization's beliefs and aims.